VISHAL SINGH

+1 (216) 650-1044 | singhspvishal@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/singhspvishal | GitHub

SUMMARY

A proficient full-stack developer with 3+ years of experience in languages like Java, front-end technologies, scripting languages, and databases with expertise in building REST APIs, orchestrating CI/CD pipelines, and utilizing various frameworks and tools to enable effective development.

EDUCATION

University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio, USA

Aug 2022 - Apr 2024

GPA: 3.96/4

Master of Computer Science

Relevant Coursework: Cloud Computing, Database Management, Software Engineering, Automation Testing, Operating System

CVR College of Engineering, Hyderabad, India Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science

Aug 2017 - May 2021

GPA: 3.8/4

SKILLS

Languages: Java, C, C#, Python, TypeScript, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, XML, SQL, NoSQL

Framework: Spring, Angular, ReactJS, StencilJS, Hibernate

Software Tools: Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes, Postman, Redux, Kafka, AWS, JUnit, Mockito, Selenium, SonarQube, JIRA

WORK EXPERIENCE

Software Engineer

Cloud Waze, Dallas, Texas

Aug 2023 - Oct 2023

- Developed an analytics dashboard leveraging Java, Angular, and RESTful services, leading to a 30% enhancement in data visualization.
- Migrated the analytics application to AWS using EC2 and RDS, resulting in a 50% boost in scalability.
- Implemented JUnit and Mockito for unit testing, ensuring a robust codebase with a 60% test coverage.

ADP. Hyderabad, India

July 2021 - July 2022

Full Stack Developer

- Designed and migrated 50% of the company web pages from AngularJS to StencilJS using typescript.
- Developed Rest APIs using JAVA to improve intersystem communication between UI and MongoDB by almost 75%.
- Leveraged Junit for unit testing and Selenium for automation testing to increase test case coverage by 35%.
- Accelerated deployment by 40% by developing a CI/CD pipeline using Jenkins and configured servers using AWS EC2.
- Managed source code using Bitbucket, improved team collaboration with Confluence, and tracked issues daily with JIRA, ensuring project consistency and efficiency through Agile development practices.

ADP, Hyderabad, India May 2020 - Feb 2021

Application Developer

- Built web applications using Angular 8, HTML5, Bootstrap, JAVA, Spring, and MongoDB facilitating more than 50k employees in storing and uploading their tax documents.
- Streamlined CI/CD pipelines using Docker, reducing build and deployment times by 40%.
- Participated in core team meetings, design reviews, and requirements sessions to understand business needs and operational procedures, aiding in project planning and execution.

Right Data, Hyderabad, India Aug 2019 - May 2020

Software Developer

- Utilized ReactJS, JAVA, and Spring Boot to establish 10+ microservices.
- Automated, mapping between MySQL databases and Java objects with Hibernate ORM reducing query writing by 50%.
- Utilized Kafka for asynchronous messaging between microservices, improving system scalability by 30% and enhancing reliability.
- Managed manual deployments and constructed CI/CD pipelines, parallelizing test runs, resulting in an 80% reduction in overall test run time.

CERTIFICATIONS

- Microsoft Certified: Azure Fundamentals.
- Database Programming with PL/SQL by Oracle.

- Database Programming with SQL by Oracle.
- Database Design by Oracle.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS

zKPass Protocol using ZKP

Feb 2024 - Apr 2024

Engineered a novel authentication method leveraging zero-knowledge proofs (ZKPs) to ensure 100% user privacy and security in blockchain networks and used JavaScript, HTML, Bootstrap, NodeJS, and JAVA to demonstrate the authentication model.

Study Room Reservation System

Sep 2023 - Dec 2023

Implemented a 75% more efficient real-time study room reservation application for the University of Cincinnati using Angular, JavaScript, and Java to ensure user interfaces with seamless front-end and back-end integration.

Number Plate Recognition System

- Automated the security systems in the parking lot using the image processing technique OpenCV and Python libraries to detect the number plates of more than 500+ cars and store the data in the MySQL database.
- Created a web page using .Net, and C# where the 500+ users can manage their accounts and make short-term and long-term payments associated with their vehicles in a parking lot based on the time stamps.

Kisan Vikas (Development of Farmers) - Mobile Application

Architected a mobile application for farmers to estimate the prices and sell their goods at profitable prices directly into the market using Android Studio, XML schemas, and learning algorithms.